下水道
KADR
导演：安杰伊•瓦依达
DIRECTED BY
1994年
1944.
9月底
Late September.
华沙起义接近它悲剧性的尾声
The Warsaw Uprising nears its tragic end.
古老的城镇，里弗赛德，测尼亚考，撒底巴早已崩溃
The Old Town, Riverside, Czerniakow and Sadyba fell long ago.
查理波，莫考淘，和市区
Zoliborz, Mokotow and the downtown areas,
都被德国军队切断和包围剩下的只有燃烧着的火焰
cut off and surrounded by massive German forces, are in flames.
这个队伍编号为43
This company now numbers 43.
三天前，还有70人
Three days ago, there were 70.
这是他们的指挥官
This is their commanding officer...
查德拉中尉
Lieutenant Zadra.
他招募了这些人，当然也要为他们负责
He recruited these men and is responsible for them.
他的副指挥，怀斯中尉
His second-in-command, Lieutenant Wise.
他对手下要求非常严格
He drilled discipline into his boys with an iron hand.
这是哈琳卡，负责通讯的女孩
And this is Halinka, the messenger girl,
她离开家的时候承诺妈妈说，她会注意保暖的
who promised her mother on leaving home that she'd keep warm.
他们可能都作过同样的承诺
They probably all made similar promises.
所有的妈妈多少一样的
All mothers are the same.
军士长布里特笔头功夫很厉害
Sergeant Major Bullet writes in a perfect hand.
所有士兵的资料他都用一个箱子扛着
He carries all the company records in his case.
卡迪特•克拉伯长官不能按时每天洗澡成了他最难受的事情
Officer Cadet Korab suffers greatly without his daily bath.
但是三排的小伙子们麻烦就更大了
But the boys of the 3rd Platoon have bigger troubles.
斯林，克拉伯的副官
Slim, Korab's aide,
希望在战后去制造飞机
hopes to build airplanes after the war.
最后是作曲家
Finally, the composer.
他不是当兵的
He's not a soldier.
他是昨天才参加到队伍中来的
He joined the company only yesterday.
这就是悲剧中的英雄们
These are the heroes of the tragedy.
仔细看清楚
Watch them closely,
因为这是他们生命的最后时刻
for these are the last hours of their lives.
嗨
Hey!
嗨，查德拉，蛮准时
Hello, Zadra. Right on time.
怎么了，受伤了？
What's that? Were you hit?
一点小问题
Just caught a little draft.
情况怎么样
What's the situation?
你看得到的，轰炸机还在那里
As you can see, the dive bombers were here.
德国人三次想踏平这里
The Germans have tried to push through three times.
还好他们晚上睡觉
Good thing they sleep at night.
看来明天就难了
You won't have an easy life here tomorrow.
好像死更容易，我们会竭力抵抗
More like an easy death. Anyway, we'll try to hold out for a while.
我也想留下来
I'd like to stay too.
留到世界末日？
What, till Judgment Day?
后代人会赞扬我们的
But we'll be hailed by future generations.
他们也没法让我们活着
They won't take us alive.
对，这是波兰
That's right. The Polish way!
怎么了，你一向都很自信的
What's wrong? You've always been a hotshot.
我受够了
I've had enough, all right?
我怎么跟我的兄弟们说，他们都相信我
What am I to tell my men? They trust me.
别悲观，在这里想也没用
You're losing your nerve. There'll be no time for brooding here.
巴提克今天已经放弃前线据点了
Bartek almost abandoned the front positions today,
好像他还有别的地方可去
as if the little shit had somewhere to go.
现在这里地方已经很小了
It's getting cramped around here.
他们想先解决莫考淘，然后开始进攻市区
They want to finish off Mokotow and start in on downtown.
我不相信，这还是起义的第56天
Damn! I can't believe it's the 56th day of the uprising.
妈的
Hell.
这是我们的选择
Yes, that's always an option.
巴桑那
Bozena!
有是吗消息
What's the news?
我们见过
We've met before.
起义的第一天你给了我这个
You gave me these the first day of the uprising.
合适吗是的
- Do they fit? - You bet.
可能我死了他们会脱走
To think they'll rip 'em off me when I die.
我知道你已经参加起义了
I see you've joined the uprising.
你妈妈怎么说
What does your mother say to that?
她死了
She's dead.
你的伤严重吗
Is your wound bad?
没事
No, it's nothing.
太严重了
Too bad you already -
对不起，这里有电话吗
Excuse me. Is there a phone around here?
那边
There will be.
我可以打到拉奎卡街去吗
Can I call Rakowiecka Street?
你疯了？德国人在那里
Are you crazy? The Germans are there.
我知道，但是…我家在那儿
I know, but you see, I live there.
让我打一个好吗
Let me call, all right?
去找指挥官
Go see the commander.
那边？
That way?
有些华沙人还过得不错
Some lived in style in Warsaw!
中产阶级的客厅，确实很豪华
A bourgeois drawing room. Absolutely appalling.
我们的手枪和手榴弹
Our pistols and grenades
对他们的坦克和飞机
against their tanks and airplanes.
我们什么时候有消息
When will we wise up?
这是命令，别去探究
Orders are orders. No sense philosophizing.
克拉伯
Korab.
安排岗哨，派一队巡逻兵出去
Post sentries and send out a patrol.
是
Yes, sir.
6位志愿者，出列
Six volunteers, step forward.
是
Yes, sir!
我有一个特殊的任务交给你们
I have a special assignment for you.
等等，你是作曲家是吗？对
- Wait. You're a composer, aren't you? - Yes.
给我们弹点好听的，我们这里有钢琴 -但是我
- Play something nice. We have a piano. - But I have -
来哇，是贝斯丁的
- Come on. - Good God, it's a Bechstein!
把那个拿开，免得振动
Take that piece of junk away. It rattles too much.
不，弹点坎巴斯塔或者其它这类的
No, play La Comparsita or something like that.
我今天梦到你了，哈琳卡
I had a dream about you today, Halinka.
我们在跳探戈
We were dancing a tango, and -
是吗消息，哈琳卡
Well? What's new, Halinka?
中尉，你答应给我一把枪的
Lieutenant, you promised me a gun.
我不想空着手，别人都有
I don't want to be empty-handed. Everyone else has something.
这么小的？我还想有一把巴拉贝雷姆呢
This little thing? I was hoping for a Parabellum.
一把巴拉贝雷姆？你拿都拿不住
A Parabellum? It'd knock you off your feet.
这个对你正合适，6英尺内可以杀人，拿着
This is just right for you. It'll kill a man at six feet. Take it.
别制造噪音了
Stop that noise.
弹点实在的
Play something
有感情的
with some feeling.
我可以给你弄一把真正的枪
I could get you a real gun,
而不是这种玩具手枪
instead of that cap gun.
玩具手枪？
Cap gun?
那你怎么还拿着这种古董
Then why do you carry such an antique?
都明白了吗 明白了
- All clear? - Yes, sir.
别发疯
Don't go crazy.
中尉
Lieutenant,
我可以打电话给拉奎卡街的家人吗
may I call my home on Rakowiecka Street?
我家人可能还在那里，我可以用这个电话吗
My family should be there. May I use this telephone?
转40218就可以了
Just ask them to put me through to 4-0-2-1-8.
好，我看看那边情况怎么样
All right. Let's see what's going on there.
查德拉，那边怎么样？你还活着？
Zadra here. How are things there? You still alive?
我们没有窗玻璃了窗玻璃？
- We've got no windowpanes. - Windowpanes?
我还真不记得什么样的了能有个屋顶你就算幸运了
I've forgotten what they look like. You're lucky to have a roof.
跟我试一下40218
Listen, can you try 4-0-2-1-8?
是我们的地方吗？不，是德国人那边的，拉奎卡
- One of ours? - No, on the German side. Rakowiecka.
那里没人了所以我想看看
- There's no one there. - That's what we want to see.
我试一下好，我等你
- I'll try. - Okay, I'll wait.
他们说那里没人了
They say there's no one there anymore.
万达？
Wanda?
是我，米考
It's me, Michal.
你那里怎么样，我一直在想办法找你
What's going on there? I've been trying to find you all this time.
你在哪里打电话
Where are you calling from?
我…在抵抗队伍里
Well... the resistance.
我参加了一个队伍
I've joined one of the units.
还有人抵抗吗
Is there still a resistance?
鬼知道为什么，但还是有人在抵抗
God only knows how, but there is.
你呢？他们在我们的大楼里
What about you? - They're in our building.
驱逐你们？可能不是的
- Deporting people? - I don't think so.
把人聚拢，用火烧死，还好你走了
Rounding people up, setting them on fire. I'm glad you got out.
万达，天啊
Wanda, my God!
还有个小的
Here's the little one.
索西亚
Zosia.
索西卡，是我，爸爸
Zosienka, it's me, Daddy.
爸爸，快点回来，他们为什么一直在开枪
Daddy, come home soon. Why do they keep shooting?
他们来抓我们了，米考
They're coming for us, Michal!
神圣的母亲，我们现在被隔离了
Holy Mother of God, we got cut off.
所有岗哨都已经安排好谢谢
- All sentries posted, sir. - Thank you.
斯林
Slim.
我现在干什么
What do I do now?
去睡觉
Go get some sleep.
大家准备吃饭
Everybody get ready for dinner!
哈琳卡，我们找个地方睡觉去
Halinka, let's find somewhere to sleep.
中尉
Lieutenant.
中尉，先生
Lieutenant, sir,
我没有克拉伯排的档案
I don't have any records of Korab's platoon.
别拿这些档案来烦我
Don't bother me with your records.
马上就要开始了
It's going to start soon.
但我们必须保留档案，可能会有伤亡
But we must keep records, sir. There will be casualties.
肯定会有伤亡
There will be casualties. That's for sure.
但你不要来烦我
But stop bothering me now!
斯林，看到什么了吗
Slim, see anything there?
没有，挖土豆的已经从田里回来了
Nothing. The potato diggers have just returned from the fields.
只有阎王知道
Only the devil knows
他们是不是可以活着吃到这些土豆
if they'll live to eat them.
如果他们再派轰炸机来，这里就平了
If they send any more dive bombers, they'll level this place.
你准备好了吗，克拉伯
Are you ready, Korab?
他们8点肯定会开始
They'll start by 8:00 for sure.
我先刮个胡子，我还有10个子弹带
I'll just shave first. I have ten ammo belts.
你多大了，克拉伯？23
- How old are you, Korab? - Twenty-three.
这个年龄，生命还不那么可贵
At that age life doesn't seem so precious.
这是我们最后的日子了
You know, these are the final days.
我知道，但我们先要让他们流血
I know, but we'll make them bleed first.
黛西回来了吗
Is Daisy back yet?
怎么了
What's wrong?
没什么
Nothing.
你知道怎么用吗
You know how to use that?
小心
Careful!
你疯了？
Are you crazy?
还没那么复杂
It's not that complicated.
你小心点
Just be careful.
我要走了，德国人马上就吃完早餐了
I'm going. The Germans will be finishing their breakfast.
你弹什么
What are you playing?
跑调了
It's out of tune.
这里太多的音乐家了
Too many musicians around here.
我走了
I'm going.
别发疯
Just don't go nuts.
失去一个艺术家很可惜的
It'd be a pity to lose an artist.
你知道什么
What do you know?
噢，对不起
Oh, sorry.
没事，进来，这怎么了
That's all right. Come in. What's this about?
你应该起来
You should get up.
这不是时候你是这样对长官说话的吗
It's hardly the time - - Is that how you speak to an officer?
这才真正是时候
Now's precisely the time for it.
我们在谈恋爱
We're in love.
黛西怎么样
And how's Daisy?
杰克，我来了
Jacek, I'm here.
我不臭吧？我把鞋子脱了走廊
I don't stink, do I? I left my shoes in the hallway.
你别再在那些下水道里跑了
It's about time you stopped wandering around those sewers.
你本来昨天就该回来的
You were supposed to be back yesterday.
你在担心我吗
Were you worried about me?
很久以前就没担心了，但查德拉问起过你
I stopped worrying long ago, but Zadra was asking about you.
你吃醋？
Are you jealous?
我
Me?
根本没有
Fat chance.
但你谁都不放过
But you spare no one.
我只是对查德拉笑笑，跟别人也是一样
I just smiled at Zadra, like I do with everyone.
对，你好像对他格外温柔
Exactly. It looked as if you had a soft spot for him.
我就是这样，无可救药
That's just how I am. It can't be helped.
可惜
Too bad.
你应该呆在市区的，你那里有很多
You should've stayed downtown, where you've got all those...
朋友
friends.
他们想解决掉我们
They're going to finish us off, here.
我知道
I know.
看我给你带什么了
Look what I brought you.
真正的英国茶和香烟
Real English tea and cigarettes.
你知道我不抽烟的
You know I don't smoke.
哪里来的
Where'd you get them?
我阿姨那里的
From my aunt.
你阿姨
Your aunt.
杰克，我是为了你才回来的
Jacek, I came back just for you.
我？有意思，为什么
Me? That's interesting. Why?
为什么？
Well? Why?
Why?
因为我是你的通讯员
Because I'm your messenger.
你知道主力攻击马上就要到这里吗
Did you know the main attack will be here?
别刮了
Stop shaving, will you?
洗一下，你好臭
Wash up. You stink.
想裸体日光浴吗
Been sunbathing in the nude?
我整个7月都在查理西
I spent all of July in Zalesie
8月1号才回到华沙，上帝才知道为什么
and got back to Warsaw on August 1st. God knows what for.
你阿姨也跟你在查理西吗
Did you stay with your aunt in Zalesie too?
我们走
Here we go!
走开，他妈的别傻
- Get out of here, damn it! - Don't be an idiot!
继续开火
Keep firing!
左边的机关枪低一点
Left machine gun lower! Lower!
小心
Watch out!
掩护
Take cover!
嘿，巴提克
Hello, Bartek?
妈的，两个电话机都没用了，他们会从后面来
Damn it, both phones are dead! They'll come from behind.
测夫在
Zefir? - Sir!
到总部去
Run to headquarters.
报告他们，我们守在红房子里，但是巴提克的队伍没了
Report that we're holding the Red House but Bartek's section is gone.
我们需要反攻，不然，我们就会被隔离
We need a counterattack, or else they'll cut us off. Go!
明白了吗，快去
Got all that? Then go!
垃圾，废管子
Junk! Useless pipe!
10分钟内他们就可以把我们解决掉
They'll finish us off in ten minutes.
撤
Withdraw.
我们用拳头是顶不住他们的，够了，他妈的
We can't stop them with our fists! Enough, damn it!
这是最后一个，斯林
That's the last shell, Slim.
斯林打中了
Slim actually hit 'em!
庞然大物
Goliaths.
别管我，我没事
Leave me alone. I'm all right.
别动
Keep still.
你没受伤吧
You're not hurt, are you?
没事就好
I'm glad you're okay.
怎么了
What's happening?
队员怎么样
What about the platoon?
德国佬在等什么
What are the Krauts waiting for?
测夫回来了吗 -还没有
Is Zefir back? - No.
我们被包围了
We're surrounded.
克拉伯怎么样
How's Korab?
他没死，应该会没事
He's alive. He'll be fine.
他们要把我的人一个个干掉
They're wiping out my men.
别伤感
Don't go soft.
这安静非常可怕只是一个短暂的停顿
- The silence is deafening. - It's only a brief pause.
他们在盘算怎么干掉我们
They're scheming how to finish us off.
前门攻不了，他们就会从厨房来
Front door didn't work, so they'll try through the kitchen.
现在是撤退的好时机，先生
Now's a good time to withdraw, sir.
中尉，你从来不抽烟的
Lieutenant, you never used to smoke.
从来？
Nerves?
怕
Fear.
这场战斗对我们所有的人都张大着嘴巴
This war's eating at all of us.
我小时候就开始抽烟
Not me. I've smoked since I was a kid.
你什么时候参加抵抗军的
When did you join the resistance?
1941年7月份
July of 1941.
勋章呢
Decorations?
攻击布兰卡
The Cross of Valor for an attack on Blanka -
布兰卡宫殿的英勇战士
An attack on Blanka Palace.
1944年9月26
Wounded in the right side of the chest
右胸受伤
on September 26th, 1944.
亲戚
Next of kin
怕死吗
in case of death?
谢谢
Thank you.
他们想到方法了
They've found a way to get to us.
他们不会动
They're not doing anything.
我改变主意了
I've changed my mind.
战后我不去做飞机
I won't build planes after the war is over.
查德拉
Zadra.
查巴瓦在找你，好像发生什么事了
Zabawa's looking for you. Something's happened.
先生，红房子指挥官报告
Sir! Company in the Red House reporting, sir.
嗨，查德拉
Hello, Zadra.
下去吧，测夫
Take off, Zefir.
伤亡情况
Losses?
12个死的，10个重伤
Twelve dead, 10 critically wounded.
天黑前你们就要离开这里我们要转移到市区去
You'll be leaving here at dusk. We're moving to the downtown area.
什么？怎么去
What? How?
通过下水道
Through the sewers.
我不去
I'm not going.
你疯了？现在只剩下几条街了
Are you crazy? Only a couple streets are left.
明天他们就可以把我们全部干光
They'll finish us off by tomorrow.
我不去
I'm not going.
流了这么多血，我们还有像老鼠一样爬
All that blood shed, and we crawl away like rats?
下水道
The sewers!
我怎么面对我的兄弟们
How can I look my men in the eyes?
这是命令，查德拉
That's an order, Zadra.
去你的命令
Screw your orders!
你毕竟还是个平民
You're a damned civilian, after all.
你不想救你的兄弟们吗
Don't you want to save your men?
他们相信我
They trusted me.
我们都在相信某个人
We all trusted someone.
这是你们到下水道的路
Here. This is your pass to the sewers.
保重，查德拉
Take care, Zadra.
为什么这么安静
Why's it so quiet in here? For God's sake!
来点音乐
So put on some music.
别吹
Stop that.
Stop that!
也许你想听交响乐吧
Maybe you'd prefer a symphony.
来，你吹
Here, you play it.
就这个？
On this thing?
自作聪明
Wiseguy.
听着，兄弟们，好消息
Listen up, kids. Good news.
什么好消息？增援？
What is it? Reinforcements?
我们要到市区去
We're crossing into downtown...
通过下水道
through the sewers.
什么意思
What do you mean?
我们要离开这里？
We're leaving here?
我们守不住莫考淘了
We can't hold Mokotow.
只剩下几条街了
There are only a few streets left.
他们会结束我们的
They'd crush us.
你们听到了吗，我们白在这里拼命的
Hear that, guys? We've been fighting in this coffin for nothing!
这是总部的命令
It's an order from headquarters.
什么都没有
Nothing.
没用
A void.
现在还是没有一个声音
Even now all I come up with are empty sounds.
别喝了
Don't drink any more, please.
我真没用，一个可怜虫
I'm impotent, understand? A pathetic hack.
这是真正的悲剧
That's the real tragedy.
请你别喝了赶快结束这折磨就好了
- Please, don't drink. - I'm glad this torment is ending.
给我，我也要
Give it to me. I want some too.
那帅小伙子爱你吗
So the handsome trooper loves you, does he?
他是你第一个吗
Is he your first?
我有预感，我们活不过今晚
Something tells me we won't live through this night.
有爱的人，死也更容易
It's easier to die when you're in love.
废话
Nonsense.
真感人
Melodrama.
别陷得太深
Don't get carried away.
给指挥官让地方
Make room for the company commander!
喝，查德拉你疯了
Drink, Zadra. - You've gone mad.
你也喝，哈琳卡
You too, Halinka?
我不喝，我听音乐
I'm not drinking. I'm listening to music.
音乐？你们现在都想听音乐吗
Music? So now you all feel like hearing music?
你在弹吗
And you're playing?
最后一次
For the last time!
喝，查德拉，可以帮助你过下水道
Drink, Zadra. It'll help you through the sewers.
这就是你的原则吗
So this is your sense of discipline?
站好最后一班岗只有死人才会喝醉
At your post till the end - only dead drunk!
到市区很远
It's a long way to downtown.
有足够的时间醒酒
Plenty of time to sober up.
到市区干什么继续战斗
- What'll we do downtown? - Keep fighting.
继续战斗？他们会把我们当臭虫一样捏死
Keep fighting? They'll squash us like bedbugs.
城市里什么都没有了
Nothing'll be left of the city.
闭嘴，死也要死得像个男人
Shut up! You can't even die like a man!
相反，现在我知道怎么去死
On the contrary. Now I know how to die.
连队点名是
- Company roll call. - Yes, sir.
现在是排，不是连了
But now it's a platoon, not a company.
别还像我们走的时候一样
Don't anyone so much as fart once we're off.
像个家族坟墓
Quiet as a family tomb.
否则，德国人会杀了我们的
Otherwise, the Germans will slaughter us.
如果谁怕，就到我这里来
If anyone's frightened, let him come to me,
我可以抓着他的手
and I'll hold his hand.
振作点，兄弟们
Well, chin up, old pals!
立正
Attention!
所有队伍都已经清点，准备行进
All present and accounted for and ready to march.
两个长官，5个军士，20个枪手
Two officers, five NCOs and 20 riflemen.
你喝醉了，这不是操练的时候
You're drunk. This is no time for drills.
谢谢
Thank you.
稍息
At ease.
前进
Forward march.
你行吗，克拉伯
Can you make it, Korab?
我走了，把那个给我
I'm going. Give me that.
让我试试，我没别的东西可以失去了
Let me try. I've got nothing to lose.
他需要两个强壮的男人
He needs two strong men.
我去照顾他，你不必担心
I'll take care of him. You needn't worry.
你最好跟着我
You'd better come with me.
你可以给我们带路
You can show us the way.
路很容易走的
The way is pretty easy.
请让我和克拉伯一起走
Please, let me go with Korab.
怀斯，掩护我们，让我们过去
Wise, cover us till we get across.
老虎坦克
Tiger tanks.
这是最后一道路障，到下水道里去吧，朋友
This is the last barricade. Get in the sewers, friend.
报告中尉，该我们
Lieutenant, may I respectfully report that it's our turn -
到下水道里去
Respectfully report into the hole.
你这个U
Why, you little -
先生，你看到我女儿了吗？她是金色的头发
Sir, have you seen my daughter? She's blonde -
我们走
Let's go!
先生，等等，等等
Gentlemen, wait! Please, wait!
我女儿是高个子，金色头发，穿棕色衣服
My daughter's tall and blonde, in a brown coat.
等一等
Please wait.
先生，同情一下我
Gentlemen, have pity.
别抛弃我们
Don't leave us!
这是什么妈的
- What is it? - Shit!
噢，这声音效果真好
Oh, God, what amazing acoustics!
”我看到一块沉重的梦境和阴影的土地”
"I see a land of heavy dreams and shadows.''
别念诗了，走
Stop with the poetry and get a move on, maestro!
安静，命令不许说话的
Quiet! The orders were no talking.
我太高了妈的
I'm too tall for - Goddamn it!
你容易点，哈琳卡
You have it easier, Halinka.
毒气，毒气
Gas! Gas!
德国佬，毒气
Germans! Gas!
怀斯，我们回去吧，前面有毒气
Wise, let's turn back. There's gas ahead.
德国人就在上面等
The Germans are up there already.
我们得赶上连队
We have to catch up with the company.
别走，那是什么
Stop! What is it?
德国佬放了毒气进来了，那是回去的路吗
The Germans let in gas! Is that the way back?
我想是的
I suppose so.
谁能肯定，所有下水道都是一样的
But who knows for sure? All these sewers look alike.
我是从老镇来的
I'm from the Old Town.
我已经受够这下水道，这捉迷藏的游戏
I've had enough of these sewers and this shitty game of hide-and-seek!
他们放毒气进来了，回去
They let in gas! Go back!
回去，有毒气
Go back, there's gas!
嘿，你们去哪里
People, where are you going?
嘿
People!
我的头在转
My head's spinning.
肯定是毒气的缘故
Must be the gas.
你在发烧，杰克，这里没毒气
You're feverish, Jacek. There's no gas here.
我们永远都赶不上了
We'll never catch up.
也许我们可以叫米考
Perhaps we should call Michal.
没必要
No need for that.
我熟悉这里的下水道
I know this sewer.
不难走
The way's not difficult.
我们自己过去，慢点
We'll make it by ourselves, slowly.
我要休息一下
I'm gonna rest a minute.
坚持走
Keep going, damn it!
杰克，坚持住，回家再休息
Jacek, keep going. You'll rest at home.
家？谁还会有家
Home? Does anyone still have a home?
你真的很顽强，黛西
You're really strong, Daisy.
你好像以前经常扛重物一样
As if you were used to carrying heavy loads.
我从来没扛过重物
I've never carried anything heavy.
其实我一点都不了解你
Actually, I know nothing about you.
我们在起义中一起战斗
We fought together in the uprising.
我知道，黛西，但是•
I know that, Daisy, but...
你现在想听我的故事吗
You want to hear my life story now?
长吗
Is it long?
比这下水道长
Longer than this sewer.
继续走
Keep going.
那是什么
What's that?
看
Look.
交叉的地方有个灯笼，到底是
A lantern at the junction? Or what in hell -
可能是德国佬
Maybe it's the Germans.
他们不敢下来的
They wouldn't dare come down here.
你肯定吗
Are you sure?
肯定
Positive.
杰克，只是个蜡烛
Jacek, it's just an ordinary candle.
这是第一道路障，你可以休息一下了
This is the first barricade. You can rest here.
谁帮我扶一下这个伤员别说话
- Someone help me lift a wounded man! - Quiet!
你看什么
What are you staring at?
别说话，德国佬就在上面
Quiet, the Germans are above us!
别出声，你这个狗杂种
Quiet, you stupid son of a bitch!
已经7点了
It's already 7:00.
我想上面已经是白天了
Just think. It's day up there.
叫怀斯中尉
Call Lieutenant Wise.
怀斯中尉，报告查德拉中尉
Lieutenant Wise, report to Lieutenant Zadra.
Lieutenant Wise, report to Lieutenant Zadra!
毒气，毒气
Gas! Gas!
要在这里讲原则很难啊，中尉
It'll be difficult to enforce discipline down here, Lieutenant.
但是命令还是要下达的，我们该怎么办
But orders must be given. What do we do?
我们等怀斯，不能把他们丢在后面
Let's wait for Wise. We can't leave them behind.
他们的火柴
Damned matches!
不是火车的问题，先生
It's not the matches, sir.
这么多人在这里面呼吸
There's too many feet stirring up this crap, releasing fumes.
这才是让我们致命的，而不是手榴弹
That's what's killing us, not the grenades.
我以前涉足过化学，你感觉很虚弱吗
I used to dabble in chemistry. Don't you feel weak, sir?
不
No!
这里已经没有氧气了
Still, there's no oxygen in this air.
我们要自己救自己，中尉
Let's save ourselves, Lieutenant.
怎么样，我们就这样让他们死吗
What about it, sir? Do we leave the men to die like this?
是我的错吗？为什么怀斯还没到
Is that my fault? Why isn't Wise here yet?
叫他
Call him!
别坐着，靠近水的地方的空气更差
Don't sit down! The air is worse near the water.
你们会起不来的
You won't be able to get up.
我们走，中尉，我们不能呆在这里了
Let's go, Lieutenant. We mustn't stay here.
那我走了
I'm going to go then.
我去叫他们
I'll call them.
怀斯中尉说我们应该先走
Lieutenant Wise says we should go ahead.
他们停下来好让克拉伯休息
They stopped so that Korab could rest.
再说，黛西熟悉路
Anyway, Daisy knows the way.
他们会赶上我们的
They'll catch up with us.
走，中尉
Let's go, Lieutenant.
走，兄弟们
Let's go, boys.
慢点，怀斯
Slow down, Wise.
快点
Hurry up.
查德拉可能已经到阿里奇地区了
Zadra's probably up in the Alejach district.
把水壶给我
Give me the canteen.
那样你会更加虚弱的
It'll just make you weaker.
来，给我
Come on, give it to me.
你要来点吗
You want some?
当然，很冷
Sure. It's cold.
我快不行了
I'm worn out.
够了
That's enough.
这是遗忘之水啊
It's the waters of Lethe,
遗忘之河
the river of oblivion.
家里酿造的，但很管用，是吗
A simple home brew, but it cheers you up, doesn't it?
你听到什么声音了吗
You hear those sounds?
快点，作曲家
Hurry up, composer.
天啊，那是什么，怀斯
Christ, what's that? Wise!
上帝
Jesus!
你没死吧，哈琳卡
Are you alive, Halinka?
维托德，你在哪里，我们的孩子在哪里
Witold! Where are you? Where's my child?
闭嘴，闭嘴，该死的女人
Shut up! Shut up, damned woman!
你把我们卖掉了，凶手
You've sold us out! Murderers!
打开
Open up!
Open it up!
让我过去
Let me through!
”我们在护城河里
"Thither we came, and thence down in the moat
我看见一个人窒息在污秽中
I saw a people smothered in filth
窒息在那漂浮着的来自人类的东西中”
That out of human privies seemed to flow''
你说什么，米考不是我说，是但丁
- What are you saying, Michal? - It's not I, child, but Dante.
我打不开
I can't open it!
下来，你们会把德国佬引来的
Get down here, damn it! You'll bring the Germans down on us!
快点
Hurry up!
怀斯，救救我们，我好怕
Wise, let's save ourselves! I'm scared.
别哭丧着脸了
Stop your whining.
你以为我不想出去吗？我们回去
Think I don't want out of here? We're going back.
你脸色很难看，杰克
You look bad, Jacek.
我们一出去，你就去刮胡子
You'll have your shave as soon as we get out.
没关系
I don't care.
你病得太厉害了
You must be very ill.
现在怎么办
Now what?
下雨
Rain?
我听到雨声了
I hear the sound of rain.
别出声
Quiet!
别叫了
Don't cry, child.
你没听到吗
Can't you hear
这里一切都在歌唱
everything here is singing?
对，你可能还听到天使的声音呢
Yeah, and maybe you're seeing angels too?
走，别停下来别出声
Come on! Don't stop! - Quiet!
听到了吗？你听
Hear that? Listen!
胡扯，是水
Nonsense! It's the water!
我听到了
I can hear it.
我终于听到了
I can finally hear it.
你知道吗
You know?
我听到了
I can hear it.
别出声
Shut up, damn you!
你怎么了，你疯了？
What's with you? Have you gone mad?
你这个荒唐的家伙
Ridiculous, rude man.
你怎么会理解呢
How could you understand?
回来，别傻
Come back here! Don't be a fool!
站住，不然我就开枪了
Stop or I'll shoot!
我命令你立即回来
I order you to come back at once!
我为什么这么虚弱
Why am I so weak?
我们永远都到不了市区
We'll never reach downtown anyway.
无路可走了
There's no way.
这他妈的下水道总也要有个结束吧
This damned sewer has to end somewhere!
走
Let's go.
那是什么
What's that?
可能是个伤员
Probably a wounded man.
人会这么嚎叫吗
Could that be a man howling like that?
继续走
Let's keep going.
先生，我真不知道那是什么声音
Sir, I can't make out those sounds.
我去看看，你们在这里等
I'll go have a look. Wait here.
就是他在叫
Here's your howler.
是个人，我们快走，先生
It's a man. Let's get out of here, sir.
我认识他
I know him.
是总部的一个上校
A colonel from headquarters.
你们谁抬他
Which one of you will carry him?
怎么了
What's the matter?
前进
Forward!
该往哪个方向
Where do we turn?
应该有到维尔查的标记在什么地方的
There should be a sign for Wilcza Street somewhere on the left.
黛西在就好了，她认识路
We should have brought Daisy with us. She knows the way.
黛西在照顾克拉伯
Daisy's taking care of Korab,
我们知道怎么认
and we know how to read.
我们认不出，中尉
We can't do it, Lieutenant.
我们出去，不然就永远出不去了
Let's get out now, or we never will. Holy Mother!
没有标记
There is no sign.
叫他们，布里特是
- Call the men, Bullet. - Yes, sir.
起来，中尉在前面等
Get up! The lieutenant is waiting!
先走
Go on ahead.
等等，我好虚弱
Wait a moment. I'm feeling weak.
我们休息一下
Let's rest.
那
There!
那里写的肯定是“维尔查”
There should be a sign that says "Wilcza.''
不，没有标记
No, there's no sign.
他们来了
- Well? - They're coming.
抓住我，查德拉
Hold on to me, Zadra.
我受够了
I've had enough of this.
你的脚别停
Just keep moving your legs.
黛西，你累吗
Daisy, aren't you tired?
我怎么会累？我又没受伤
Why should I be? I'm not wounded.
这里很安静，很黑暗但是
It's quiet and murky but
我们在走过一片黑暗而芳香的森林
we're walking through a dark and fragrant forest.
我们在大粪里蹒跚
We're stumbling through stinking shit.
你说话老这么直接，黛西
You're always straight to the point, Daisy.
你永远都不会爱，是吗
You could never fall in love, could you?
什么
What?
别停下来
Keep moving your legs...
不然我们要三天才能到那里
or it'll take us three days to get there.
你发烧很厉害，我们会饿死的
You're running a high fever, and we'll starve to death here.
怎么了
What's wrong?
没什么
Nothing.
那是什么
What's that?
他老了
He was old.
可能是毒气恐慌时被吓死的
Probably frightened to death during the gas panic.
傻瓜，从来没到过下水道
Stupid people. Never been in the sewers before.
不，我什么都看不见
No, I don't see anything.
在那里，标记
There it is, guys! The sign!
我       爱
"I... love...
杰克”
Jacek.''
噢，上帝
Oh, God.
我的头在旋转
My head's spinning.
可能空气中有毒气
Maybe there's gas in the air.
看看这些雾
Look at the fog.
你真是个孩子，杰克因为发烧，所以你就有了幻觉
You're a child, Jacek. The fever's making you see things.
等等，这是我们的下水道
Wait, this is our sewer.
看，维尔查
See it? Wilcza.
我一个人是肯定看不到的
I would never have noticed it on my own.
我现在几乎什么都看不到了
I can barely see anything now.
我们上去，把手给我
Let's go up. Give me your hand.
我来了
I'm coming.
你的手
Your hand.
抓住我
Hold on to me!
我爬不上去了，我不行的
I can't climb up there. I can't make it.
黛西，你一个人上去吧
Daisy, go on by yourself.
傻瓜
You idiot!
你拉我不上去的
You can't pull me up there.
走，黛西，去找人来帮忙
Go, Daisy. You'll bring help.
我就等在这里休息
I'll just rest here and wait.
看，那里有个标记
Look. There's a sign over there.
大写字母
Large letters.
"I love...''
我们要节约电池
We have to save the batteries.
那里写了字
There's some writing up there.
写什么
What does it say?
”我爱
"I love...
杰里克”
Janek.''
谁会这么乱写
Who could have written such nonsense?
不是乱写
It's not nonsense.
空荡荡的下水道
Empty sewers.
德国佬就在出口等着，这是恐惧，你知道吗
Germans at the hatch up there. It's fear, you understand?
别人写了，感觉就舒服点
Someone wrote it, and it made them feel better.
我也从这里去过
I used to pass this way too.
你写的什么
And what did you write?
“去死吧”
"Kiss my ass''
还有其它之类的
and other things like that.
杰里克是谁
And who's this Janek?
一个女孩爱着的男孩
A guy that some girl loved.
很爱吗
A lot?
是的
Yes.
非常爱，杰克
Very much, Jacek.
来，走
Come on, let's go.
不，我们上不去的，代西
No, we'll never make it, Daisy.
我就等在这里休息
I'll just wait and rest here.
你会很快找人来帮忙的
You'll bring help soon, won't you?
起来
Get up!
不嘘
- No. - Quiet!
我一定想到了
I must have just imagined it.
我的头转得这么快
My head's whirling so fast...
我还能听到音乐
I can even hear music.
噢，是发烧
Oh, right. It's the fever.
不，我真的听到了
No, I can really hear it.
Who was that?
他疯了，还是我疯了
Has he gone mad, or have I?
他早就疯了，不记得了吗
He's been mad for a while. Don't you remember him?
奇怪
Strange.
我什么都不记得了
I don't remember a thing.
米考
Michal.
米考，回来
Michal, come back!
别出声
Quiet.
他听不到你喊的
He can't hear you anyway.
别哭泣了
Stop sniveling, damn it!
我们走
Let's go!
我上不去的
I won't make it up there,
但我还想活
but I want to live.
好了，杰克，放心，你会活下来的
All right, Jacek. Don't worry - you'll live.
我们就从这里直走
We'll go straight that way.
下水道应该很快就到维斯图拉河了
The sewer should run into the Vistula soon.
这里干的，附近肯定有出口
It's dry here. There must be an exit nearby.
把手电筒打开
Turn on the flashlight.
电池不行了，我们还是要到达那里的
The battery's weak. We'll get there anyway.
不
No.
不行
It can't be.
我没力气了
I have no strength left.
我们出不去的
We're never getting out of here.
这就是头 -什么意思？
This is the end. - What do you mean?
什么头？不，我还要为别人活着
What end? No! I've got someone to live for!
我就在这里，你还要为谁活着
I'm right here. Who do you have to live for?
你什么意思，谁？我妻子和孩子
What do you mean, who? My wife and child!
你妻子和孩子？
Your wife and child?
笑话
Funny.
你从来就没提过
You never mentioned them.
你没带结婚戒指
You weren't wearing a wedding ring.
是吗，我有
Really? I have it right here.
看
Look.
看到了吗？我得活下去
See? I have to live.
我们会下水道去
Let's go back up the sewer.
快，趁我还能站起来
Quick, while I'm still on my feet!
等等
Just a minute.
把手电筒关了
Turn off the light, Wise.
来，起来
Come on, get up!
黛西，让我坐一下
Daisy, let me sit a moment.
不
No.
我要
I have to...
我要休息一下
I have to rest.
杰克，我们马上就可以到河边了
Jacek, we'll be at the river soon.
我的眼睛打不开
I can't open my eyes.
好痛
They hurt.
那就别打开
Then don't.
是因为你发烧
It's the fever.
你要到医院去住一段时间
You'll have to stay in the hospital quite a while.
医院在哪里
Where's this hospital?
你不觉得我们还可以活着出去吗
What, don't you think we'll get our lives back?
永远不可能
Never.
活着，黛西
To live, Daisy.
我向你保证
I promised you that.
我对你那么粗鲁
I was so rude to you -
我们以后再算这笔帐吧
We'll settle that later.
我不行了
I've been bad.
我看到前面有光了，杰克
I see light ahead, Jacek.
我们可以活了
We're going to live.
别打开眼睛，光线太强
Don't open your eyes. It's too bright.
还很远吗
Is it much further?
我看到了水，杰克
I see water, Jacek...
还有绿色的草地
and green grass.
那我们就去那里
Let's go there...
黛西
Daisy.
你现在可以休息了
You can rest now.
我们马上就到草地上去
We'll come out onto the grass soon.
不，别睁开眼睛
No, don't open your eyes...
因为太阳出来了
because the sun's come out.
把手举起来
Hands up!
把结婚戒指给我
Give me the wedding ring.
出来，出来
Come out! Come out!
斯林，把枪丢了
Slim, throw that damned gun away.
我们还要去救人，你就要结束了自己
We've got to save people. You're going to kill yourself.
我好晕，他妈的
That stunned me, damn it.
丢了，我们去找些新鲜空气
Throw it away. Let's get some fresh air.
走开
Get lost!
光
Light!
空气，先生
Air, sir!
我们找到出口了，告诉他们，布里特
We're going to the inlet. Tell the men, Bullet.
出口
The inlet...
我们向左转，兄弟们，我们出去了
We're turning left, guys. We're going to the inlet.
他们来了，中尉
They're coming, Lieutenant.
他们来了
They're coming.
不行
No good.
堵死了
It's blocked.
如果还有力气的话
We're turning back...
我们还是回去
if we've got the strength.
我要让我的兄弟们出去
I have to get my men out.
先生，我们要呼吸点新鲜空气
Sir, we must have some air.
那里面是死亡
It's death back there!
他们还吊了手榴弹，这些狗娘养的
They've hung grenades, the dirty bastards!
坚持一下
Hold on.
好
Good.
还有一个我们就可以出去了
Just one more and we're on our way.
走，出去，中尉
Let's go. Let's go outside, Lieutenant.
感谢你，上帝
Thank you, Mother of God.
中尉，我们这是在哪里
Lieutenant, where are we?
为什么他们没有出来
Why aren't they coming out?
叫他们，布里特
Call them, Bullet.
我们安全了
We're safe.
终于呼吸到新鲜空气了
Fresh air at last.
我们走吧，先生
Let's get away, sir.
布里特，叫他们，他们可能会走远的
Bullet, call them. They might have gone too far.
他们早就丢在后面了
They fell behind long ago.
我只是假装他们跟着
I only pretended they were behind us.
你这个混蛋
You bastard!
我的连队？
And my company?
他们还在里面？
They're still in there?
我的连队
My company.